Inventory of the Thomas A. Lane papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Thomas A. Lane papers
1942, 1947-1976
90030
Hoover Institution Archives
12 manuscript boxes (4.6 linear feet)
A major general in the United States Army and conservative columnist, lecturer, and author, the bulk of the collection reflects Lane’s interests in American foreign and military policy, the Vietnam War, religious political issues, communism, and activities of Americans for Constitutional Action (ACA) and other conservative and anti-communist organizations from 1947 to 1976. The collection is primarily Composed of speeches, writings, notebooks/notes, correspondence, conference folders full of event items, press releases, and news clippings, with some handwritten documents.
Lane, Thomas A., 1906-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1990.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1906 Born in Revere, Massachusetts
1928 Graduated with honors from the United States Military Academy Commissioned as a Second Lieutenant in the Corps of Engineers, U.S. Army
1935-1939 Served as instructor in the United States Military Academy, teaching military history
1939-1943 Served as Executive Officer to the Air Engineer, Headquarters, Army Air Force, Washington, D.C.
1943 Joined the Engineer Staff of General Douglas MacArthur at General Headquarters, Southwest Pacific Area Awarded the Distinguished Service Medal for serving as Executive Officer and Operations Officer to the Chief Engineer, GHQ, participating in plans and operations of the campaigns from New Guinea to Japan
1945 Served as a member of the Joint Operations Review Board preparing Joint Doctrine for the Army, Navy and Air Force in Washington, D.C.
1946-1948 Served as Engineer Instructor at the Air Command and Staff School, Air University, Maxwell Field, Alabama
1947-1948 Served as Chief of the Logistics Division at the Air Command and Staff School, Air University, Maxwell Field, Alabama Served as District Engineer at Little Rock, Arkansas
1950-1952 Served as District Engineer on Okinawa in the Ryukyu Islands
1952 Served one year as a student at the National War College
1953 Served one year as Assistant to the Chief of Engineers, U.S. Army for Policy Planning
1954 Served as Engineer Commissioner of the District of Columbia
1955 Promoted to Brigadier General
1957 Promoted to Major General
1957-1960 Served as Commanding General of Fort Leonard Wood, Missouri
1960-1962 Served as President of the Mississippi River Commission and Division Engineer of the Lower Mississippi Valley Division of the Corps of Engineers at Vicksburg, Mississippi
1962 Retired as a U.S. Army Major General Upon retirement, he was awarded an Oak Leaf Cluster for his Distinguished Service Medal
1962 - Served as President of Americans for Constitutional Action and served as Military Analyst of the St. Louis Globe Democrat, writing about U.S. military and foreign policy
1962-1964 Served as Executive Director of the Institute for Human Progress, Inc.
1975 Died
Sources: Biographical Sketch of Thomas A. Lane (Box-Folder 11: 3) "Essential Elements of a Conservative Program" by Thomas A. Lane (Box-Folder 4: 2-4) Thomas A. Lane, Military Times Hall of Valor website, http://projects.militarytimes.com/citations-medals-awards/recipient.php?recipientid=100249, Accessed December 12, 2014
Scope and Content of Collection
The bulk of the collection spans from 1947 to 1976, reflecting Lane’s interests in American foreign and military policy, the Vietnam War, religious political issues, communism, and activities of Americans for Constitutional Action (ACA) and other conservative and anti-communist organizations. The collection is primarily Composed of speeches, writings, notebooks, correspondence, conference folders full of event items, press releases, and news clippings, with some documents handwritten.
Lane's collection has letters, manuscripts, and other writings. Specifically, it has letters related to his career as a news columnist after his retirement as a U.S. Army Major General, to books he has written, and documents related to speaking engagements, which include his own and others speeches. The collection contains manuscripts for speaking engagements, news articles, and books, as well as collected writings from others to use as reference materials. In addition, Lane wrote about his trips, including conferences and conventions that he attended, and kept documents about his travels.
Americans for Constitutional Action (Organization); United States. Army--Officers.; Anti-communist movements--United States.; Communism.; Conservatism.; United States--Foreign relations--1945-1989.; United States--Military policy.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.
- Correspondence, 1953-1975
  Contains letters pertaining to Lane’s contributions as a columnist about public policy issues, as an author, and as a speaker.
  - Letters and Writings to Editors, 1953-1972 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Admiral Ben Moreell, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    Composed of letters and related documents between Lane and Moreell and regards Lane and Moreell.
  - General Correspondence: Mainly Unanswered, undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
    Composed of letters and related documents to Lane regarding issues in Vietnam, his writings, other people’s writings, conferences, the communist revolution, and Nationalist China, among other issues.
  - Speaking Engagements, 1969-1973 (Box-folder 1: 4-8)
    Composed of letters to and from Lane regarding talks, addresses, lectures, and speeches he gives. File also has handwritten notes.
  - Editors: To and From, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 1: 9-11)
    Composed of letters to and from editors regarding Lane’s contributions to news columns.
  - Fan Mail: No Answer Required, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 1: 12-13)
    Composed of letters to Lane regarding his news articles and books.
  - Fan Mail: Answered by Thomas A. Lane, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Composed of letters to and from Lane regarding his news articles and books that touch on political issues.
  - General Correspondence: No Answer Required, 1972 (Box-folder 2: 2-4)
    Composed of letters and post cards and related documents to Lane that touch upon Lane’s articles and books, Vietnam War, the Armed Forces, pacifism, Patriotic Education, Inc., the Panama Canal, and Equal Rights Amendment, among other issues.
  - General Correspondence: Answered by Thomas A. Lane, 1972-1973, 1975 (Box-folder 2: 5-7)
    Composed of letters from Lane regarding the Manion Forum, Socialism, Republic of Vietnam, the Defense Department, and Lane’s articles and books, among other issues.
- Speeches and Writings, 1947-1976
  Contains articles Lane wrote for newspapers; handwritten notes and drafts; drafts and proofs of his books; and speeches, addresses, and talks he gave; along with documents pertaining to speaking engagements by others.
  - Handwritten Writings, 1947-1953 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    Composed of an unbound notebook including a soliloquy on war, and notes on foreign policy, democracy, Latin America, European Federation, British Policy on European Federation, a handwritten chronology, and The War for the World draft.
  - Policy, 1951, and undated (Box-folder 2: 9)
    Composed of handwritten notes and manuscripts (“War and Peace” and “On War”) related to policy.
  - "Working Materials", 1951-1956, and undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
    Composed of handwritten and manuscript drafts and edits for his articles or books. File also has extra copies of talks.
  - General talks, addresses, statements, and lectures made by Lane and others, 1952, 1956-1972, and undated (Box-folder 3: 2-3)
  - An Address by Dr. Charles Malik to the John Carroll Society, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    Composed of Malik’s talk along with a letter to Lane that enclosed the talk.
  - "Talks Addresses and Speeches by Major General Thomas A Lane 1960-1972" (Box-folder 3: 6-8)
  - The Leadership of President Kennedy proofs and manuscript, 1964 (Box-folder 3: 9-11, Box-folder 4: 1)
  - General articles and manuscripts, 1964-1975, and undated (Box-folder 4: 2-4)
    Composed of manuscripts; handwritten notes; edits; photocopies of articles and actual articles for "Public Affairs" column (newspaper partially in German), Human Events, manuscript editorials for The Cincinnati Enquirer; article for the Manion Forum, correspondence, "Essential Elements of a Conservative Program" analysis, and news clippings written by Lane or about Lane from various newspapers (many from his "Public Affairs" column) about Electoral College, war in Vietnam, Ronald Reagan, GOP, Secretary McNamara, Hungarian revolution, military affairs, among other issues.
  - Speaking Engagement Identification Cards, 1968 (Box-folder 4: 5)
    Composed of cards identifying potential speakers (many are professors) for television, radio, congressional hearings, position papers, and debates.
  - The War for the World book final proof, 1968 (Box-folder 4: 6-7)
  - Notebooks and Notes, 1969-1973, and undated (Box-folder 4: 8-9, Box-folder 5: 1-2)
    Composed of handwritten notes about speaking engagements and potential drafts for his articles or books.
  - "The Wanderer" article, 1970 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - America on Trial: The War for Vietnam, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 5: 4-7)
    Composed of notebooks of handwritten manuscript, typed manuscript of book, correspondence with publisher about the book, handwritten notes, and a forward from A.C. Wedemeyer for the book.
  - "Public Affairs" articles for release, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 5: 8-10)
  - "Talks to be typed", 1972 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    Composed of handwritten writings about Palm Beach and Pebble Beach.
  - Paul Scott: Washington News - Intelligence Syndicate, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 6: 2)
    Composed of correspondence between Paul Scott and Lane about Lane’s “Public Affairs” column, correspondence between Lane and others pertaining to “Public Affairs”, and other related materials.
  - Lists of Publishers and Bookstores, undated (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - The Failure of the Two Party System book drafts, undated (Box-folder 6: 4-7)
    Composed of two handwritten drafts (one written in a notebook) and a typed 1st draft.
  - "Public Affairs" articles, 1973, and undated (Box-folder 6: 8-9)
    Composed of articles without “for release” explicitly stated.
  - Two Party Failure book master copy, undated (Box-folder 7: 1-3)
    Manuscript version with edits and inserts.
- References File, 1954-1974
  References File contains writings by others that Lane used as reference materials.
  - Politics, 1954, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    Composed of brochures, news clippings, and booklet about Senator Goldwater, GOP, and other issues.
  - Foundation for Economic Education, Inc. articles and brochure, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - Religion - Prayer, Constitution, Schools, Catholicism, 1960-1965 (Box-folder 7: 6-7)
    Composed of news articles, paper, talk, and booklet.
  - Congo, 1961-1963 (Box-folder 8: 1)
    Composed of news clipping, memoranda, and booklets.
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1961, 1963, 1964, 1969 (Box-folder 8: 2)
    Composed of a news article, Notes on ADA, Congressional Record Vol. 3, and a memorandum.
  - Admiral Ben Moreell, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 8: 3-5)
    Composed of booklets and addresses written by Moreell, an article by Moreell for the Manion Forum, excerpt from a letter by Moreell, and a book manuscript.
  - Cuba, 1961-1966 (Box-folder 8: 6-7)
    Composed of an unidentified writing, news clippings, reports, and a speech.
  - Defense Policy, 1961-1966 (Box-folder 8: 8-9)
    Composed of news clippings, news releases, summary about Cold War, statements, speech, address, newsletter, and correspondence.
  - Southeast Asia, 1961-1974 (Box-folder 8: 10-11, Box-folder 9: 1)
    Composed of writings by others, such as newspaper and magazine clippings and issues, press releases, and memoranda.
  - General Policy, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 9: 2-4)
    Composed of newspaper clippings and news releases, documents from Congressional Record and Fact Sheet from Internal Revenue Service; documents about Medicare, GOP health plans, Life Line Program, political platforms, Senator Goldwater, address by Major General Ellsworth I. Davis, American Association of University Professors, among others.
  - Communism, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 9: 5-6)
    Composed of news clippings, reports, brochures, notices, and booklets, quotation, correspondence, and booklet.
  - Segregation, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 9: 7, Box-folder 10: 1)
    Composed of news clippings, booklets, Congress documents, brochures, and The Catholic Lawyer magazine.
  - North Atlantic Treaty Organization, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 10: 2)
    Composed of press conference speech, addresses, remarks, and news clippings.
  - General mixed formats, 1963-1974 (Box-folder 10: 3-4)
    Composed of news articles, 1964 Report to Shareholders, bookmark of handwritten quotes, brochure about social security, Triumph magazine, Crusade for a Christian Civilization news, newsletters about security, senate, Commander Alvarez, United Nations Treaty agreement, tax prophecy, statements, American Indian Religion, Red China, and a few other issues.
  - "More Broken Piecrusts" The Red Line Release, 1964 (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - Bulletins, 1964-1968 (Box-folder 10: 6)
    Composed of a bulletin "Marxmanship" and photocopies of other bulletins.
  - Disarmament, 1965, 1973 (Box-folder 10: 7)
    Composed of booklets, Arms Control and Disarmament Act text, reports, speech, addresses, and news release.
  - House Subcommittee on Far East, 1966 (Box-folder 10: 8)
    Composed of “The War in Viet Nam and Red China” report, Harper’s Magazine (February 1966), and a press release statement.
  - The Department of Justice, amicus curiae, 1968, and undated (Box-folder 10: 9)
    Composed of a memorandum about "The Department of Justice as National Policy Maker" and a "not for direct quotation" about "The Department of Justice as Amicus Curiae" along with attached documents.
  - National Federation of Independent Business, Inc., 1969 (Box-folder 10: 10)
  - David Halberstam and Theodore H. White quotes, pink and white copies, 1973 (Box-folder 10: 11)
  - Pierre Desounettes, undated (Box-folder 10: 12)
    Composed of The State book manuscript with edits and an envelope that's addressed to Mr. Pierre Desounettes.
- Biographical File, 1942-1974
  Biographical File contains handwritten notes, notes about trips, his organization interests, paraphernalia related to his work as a newspaper columnist, and a biographical sketch.
  - American Good Government Society, 1942, 1949, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 10: 13)
    Composed of a reception and dinner invitation, document of Board of Trustees, correspondence, "Political Realignment: A Big Gain for Republicans" paper, Recorder of Deeds, and notes about presidential voting.
  - National War College Course Work, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 10: 14)
  - South America Trip notebook, 1963 (Box-folder 10: 15)
    Composed of handwritten notes about Lane’s South America trip.
  - East Asia Trip file, 1968, 1970 (Box-folder 10: 16)
    Composed of memoranda, photographs with captions on their backs, envelope of paid bills, paraphernalia, greeting cards, handwritten notes, letter about Lane, itinerary, and dinner invitation.
  - General, 1952-1972 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    Composed of a variety of documents pertaining to societies, clubs, committees, and boards in which Lane had interest. File also includes a GOP newsletter and information of interest (such as rosters) regarding Department of the Army and the National War College, places he attended, press releases, and dinner invitations.
  - Mailing List, 1964 (Box-folder 11: 2)
  - Biographical Sketch of Thomas A. Lane, 1964 (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - American Conservative Union, 1964-1965, 1973 (Box-folder 11: 4)
    Composed of a folder of correspondence, statements, brochures, memoranda, proposed budget, advisory assembly lists, confidential preliminary report, constitution and bylaws, prospectus, and agenda. File also contains a statement from Lawrence D. Pratt, Executive Director.
  - Americans for Constitutional Action, 1964-1968 (Box-folder 11: 5-7)
    Composed of correspondence, brochure, schedule of events, insert, newspaper clippings, meeting minutes, memoranda, news release, and mid-year report.
  - National Foreign Policy Conference for Editors and Broadcasters, 1966 (Box-folder 11: 8)
    Composed of a folder of program, conference information, bulletins, facts about the foreign aid program,and booklets.
  - National Strategy Seminar at US Army War College, 1969 (Box-folder 11: 9)
    Composed of "Biographic Sketches", program, guest list, locator map, position descriptions, proposal, index, memoranda, list of hospitals, officers roster, reception invitations, weekly schedule, brochures, and lecture program.
  - American Newspaper Publishers Association Convention, 1969 (Box-folder 11: 10)
    Composed of booklets and bulletins: ANPA Annual Report 1968 – Trends in the Newspaper Business, Convention Reports, details of "Count Down for the '70's" discussion sessions program, 1969 Convention Bulletin Annual Report, a floor plan of the Hotel, and Annual Report 1968.
  - Manuscript Newspaper Edits, circa 1969 (Box-folder 12: 1-2)
    Composed of cuts of manuscripts for newspapers. These pieces of paper were found in opened envelopes that state "Newspaper Only".
  - United States Strategic Institute, 1972 (Box-folder 12: 3)
    Composed of an itinerary, correspondence, a message from the directors, and agenda.
  - The Cardinal Society of Virginia, 1973 (Box-folder 12: 4)
    Composed of documents pertaining to bylaws, a meeting, and a letter.
  - Seating List for Lafayette Freedom Award Dinner, 1974 (Box-folder 12: 5)
  - Young Americans for Freedom brochure, undated (Box-folder 12: 6)